Finding Aid for Workmen's Circle/Arbeter Ring, Michigan District records, 1934-2007
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Workmen's Circle/Arbeter Ring, Michigan District records 1934-2007
Workmen's Circle/Arbeter Ring, Michigan District.
1 oversize folders
5.5 linear feet
86353 Bj 2; Bj Out.
The Workmen's Circle/Arbeter Ring Michigan District is a Jewish fraternal organization. The records cover the period between 1934 and 2007 and consist primarily of minutes, newsletters, correspondence, newspaper clippings, press releases, yearbooks, event announcements, programs, photographs, publications and posters.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was donated in 1964 as a gift of the organization (donor no. 4212 ), with an additional accession in March, 2009.
Periodic additions to the papers are expected.
The record group is open to research.
The Workmen's Circle/Arbeter Ring was formed in New York City in 1892 as a mutual aid society to provide assistance to newly immigrated Jewish workers. More than a fraternal organization, the organization assisted both in providing basic sick, death and health benefits and in supporting these workers in areas of education, cultural diversions, and as participant with them in the trade union movement. Although extant records do not make clear the founding date of the Michigan District of the Workmen's Circle, it was sometime after 1900, probably in the early 1930s.
The activities of the organization in the period covered by the records included the sponsorship of lectures and cultural events and support for the labor movement and other liberal and civil rights causes. When the members of the CIO Shoe Workers in Rockford, Michigan, went out on strike in 1952, the Workmen's Circle provided food to the striking workers. Each year, the organization gave community awards to individuals in the labor movement, civil rights struggle, or politics. In addition, the organization has maintained a dedication to education, providing Circle youth with a secular/cultural approach to the teaching of Jewish history, holidays, customs and ethics.
The records of the Workmen's Circle/Arbeter Ring cover the period between 1934 and 2007. The record group consists primarily of minutes, newsletters, correspondence, newspaper clippings, press releases, yearbooks, event announcements, programs, photographs, publications and posters. The records are arranged into four series: Administrative, Local Branches, Community Activities/Topical Files, and Events.
Subjects:
Cooperative societies--Michigan.; Detroit (Mich.); Jews--Michigan.; Social service--Michigan--Societies, etc.
- Administrative
  Administrative series documents the organizational structure and functions of the Workmen's Circle/Arbeter's Ring. Included in the series are seven volumes of minutes from the organization's early period. The Minute Books are largely written in Yiddish. The series also contains newsletters, press releases, correspondence and material related to the different district conferences and committees within the Michigan District. All material has been arranged chronologically.
  - Minute Books 1934-1963, 7 volumes (Box 1)
    (in Yiddish)
  - Administrative background 1951-2001, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Meeting announcements 1954-1959 (Box 2)
  - Meeting minutes 1949-1966 (Box 2)
  - Detroit District Committee Meeting Minutes and Reports 1976-1988, 5 folders (Box 2)
  - Detroit Biennial District Conference 1963-1991, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Michigan District Committee 1954-2001, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Biennial Michigan District Conference 1993-2003, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Great Lakes Regional Board 1969-1988 (Box 2)
  - Public Affairs Committee 1945, 1948-1949 (Box 2)
  - Organization Committee 1960, 1976-1977 (Box 2)
  - English-Speaking Division 1949-1958, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Women's Division Yearbooks, event programs 1962-1968 (Box 2)
  - Misc. yearbooks and event programs 1973, 1978 (Box 2)
  - Cemetery Department 1956-2002 (Box 2)
    (certificate in oversize folder)
  - Cemetery Department Notebook undated (Box 2)
  - The Circle Light
    - 1940-1941 (Box 3)
    - 1942-1944 (Box 3)
    - 1945-1947 (Box 3)
  - The Circle 1998-2005, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Circle Newsletter 1990-2007, 6 folders (Box 3)
    (includes upcoming calendar, tributes, and monthly director's report)
  - English-Speaking Division Newsletter 1947-1959, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - WC Calendar Newsletter 1949-1990 (Box 3)
  - Newsletter, misc. 1942, 1999 (Box 3)
  - Press Releases 1953-1999, 4 folders (Box 3)
  - Correspondence
    - 1943-1951 (Box 3)
    - 1953 (Box 3)
    - 1954-1955 (Box 3)
    - 1956-1957 (Box 3)
    - 1958-1964 (Box 3)
    - 1965-1977 (Box 3)
    - 1978-2005 (Box 3)
- Local Branches
  Local Branches series contains material originating from six local branches making up the Michigan District and the Women's Division. The series consists of mailings, newsletters, minutes, event announcements, yearbooks, and programs. Of the local branches, Branch 460 is the best documented. However, the material for each branch represents only a small portion of the local branch's history and, therefore, is not highly representative of the day-to-day activities of the different branches.
  - Branch 111, Debs
    - Mailing 1963-1977 (Box 3)
    - Yearbooks and event programs 1946-1975, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Yearbooks and event programs 1946-1975, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Branch 156
    - Yearbooks and event programs 1956, 1967-1971, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Branch 460, Emile Zola
    - General 1941-1982, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Minutes 1939-1941 (Box 4)
    - Newsletters 1957-1992, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Branch 463-E, newsletters 1957-1959 (Box 4)
  - Branch 684, Russian
    - General 1975-1980, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Events 1978-1994, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Branch 1060
    - Newsletters 1957-1958 (Box 4)
- Community Activities/Topical Files
  Community Activities/Topical Files series underscores the Workmen's Circle/Arbeter Ring's commitment to building a strong and supportive community dedicated to fostering Jewish culture and heritage. The series contains two sub-series: Membership and Other Material. Sub-series Membership includes background material such as brochures and flyers detailing the benefits of membership. The sub-series also contains membership rosters from the 1950s and material detailing the lives of individual members, either in the form of biographies or eulogies. Sub-series Other Material has been arranged alphabetically by heading. The sub-series contains correspondence, flyers, mailings, newspaper clippings, photographs and press releases. The material underscores the variety of cultural, educational, and social benefits associated with the Workmen's Circle.
  - Membership
    - Membership/Background Material 1947-1995, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Membership Rosters 1953-1958 (Box 4)
    - Community Member Biographies undated (Box 4)
    - Eulogies/Memorials 1962-2003 (Box 4)
    - Tribute Book 1990s (Box 4)
    - Russian Immigrant Community 1975-1977, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Other Material
    - Curriculum Outlines and Material undated (Box 4)
    - Educational Center
      - Background material 1985-2003 (Box 4)
      - Correspondence and announcements 1960-1995 (Box 4)
    - Fair Employment Practices Act 1945, 1955 (Box 4)
    - Group Portraits 1940s-1960s (Box 4)
    - Insurance and Medical Policy material 1953-1955 (Box 4)
    - Jewish Labor Committee 1948-1966, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - "Labor Reports," 1956-1957 (Box 4)
    - Leon A. Cousen Scholarship 1955-1959 (Box 5)
    - Music/Songs 1954, 2003 undated (Box 5)
    - Newspaper Clippings
      - 1950s, 7 folders (Box 5)
      - 1960s-1980s (Box 5)
      - 1990s-2000s, 4 folders (Box 5)
    - Rockford Shoe Workers Strike 1953 (Box 5)
    - Scrapbooks
      - 1975-1977 (Box 5)
      - 1976-1978 (Box 5)
      - 1978-1981 (Box 5)
    - WC Schools 1952-1960 (Box 5)
    - Youth Group 1953-1955 (Box 5)
- Events
  Events series reflects the wide variety of social, cultural and civic activities offered by the Workmen's Circle/Arbeter Ring. The majority of events have a focus of strengthen a secular/cultural Jewish identity. Events include holiday observations and celebrations, discussion sessions, speakers, Warsaw Ghetto Uprising Commemoration, Third Seder, Yiddish concerts, Yiddish films, musical programs, chorus, picnics, potlucks, and bazaars. The series contains event announcements, posters, programs and background material for specific events.
  - Event announcements and materials
    - undated, 4 folders (Box 5)
    - 1940-1949 (Box 5)
    - 1950-1954 (Box 5)
    - 1955-1956 (Box 5)
    - 1957, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - 1958, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - 1961-2007, 4 folders (Box 6)
  - Event Posters 2000s (Folder 1)
  - Clothes for Korea Drive 1953 (Box 6)
  - Award Ceremony Programs 1998-2003 (Box 6)
  - Father and Son Banquet 1953 (Box 6)
  - "A Kumzitz: The Schmooze Café," 1998-2005 (Box 6)
  - Celebrate Yiddish Programs 2004-2007 (Box 6)
  - Yiddish Concert in the Park 1982-1990 (Box 6)
    (includes a poster in the oversize folder)
  - Yiddish Seminar Ann Arbor 1986-1987 (Box 6)
  - Warsaw Ghetto Uprising Commemoration and Memorial 1954-2007 (Box 6)
  - Religious Holiday Service Programs 1950s-2000s, 4 folders (Box 6)